DAN KLEIN: OK.
So when we decide to use Expectimax,
and when we decide to use Minimax,
we're making modelling assumptions.
So we're back to this case of trying
to figure out based on how we think
the world works, what computation
we should do.
And in this case, there are a lot of
modeling assumptions going on.
There's what are the utilities
in Expectamax or Minimax.
There's what are the chance
probabilities that we compute in
Expectimax.
But fundamentally, a key modeling choice
is are the outcomes out of our
control adversarial or chance?
Now, it's dangerous to get it wrong.
And it's dangerous in
either direction.
So in fact, optimism and pessimism
can both be dangerous.
Why can optimism be dangerous?
Optimism can be dangerous because you
assume that things are only happening
according to chance, when the world
really is out to get you.
It's something like this.
You're wandering down, you think,
oh, those bad things
aren't going to happen.
If those bad things are actually
adversaries and they're after you,
you're going to do dangerous
things, right?
I mean, you're basically going
to get mugged a lot.
What about pessimism?
Why is pessimism dangerous?
Pessimism is dangerous because you
assume the worst possible imaginable
case, even when it's
extremely unlikely.
So it could be a vampire bunny.
Now, that's all nice and
good at a high level.
How does this play out in terms
of the actual search?
Well, we can simulate these things.
So I can take this board shown here, and
I can run a simulation of Pac-Man
trying to eat that dot, and the
ghost doing whatever it does.
And I can run it in lots
of different ways.
I can say that is a random ghost, and
I have an Expectimax Pac-Man.
And then I can run a simulation
and see what happens.
So let's take a look at what happens
with various combinations of actual
ghost behavior, and the modeling choice
that Pac-Man makes by running
Minimax or Expectimax.
Let's start with the case of the ghost
is actually random, and Pac-Man models
that correctly, meaning
Expectmax search.
Well, what's going to happen?
What's going to happen is you basically
go straight for the dot.
Because sure, the ghost could
come for you, but you know
it's wandering around.
What are the chance it's actually
going to end up on top of you?
So you go pretty much straight
towards the ghost.
You take a risk, and it
works out in general.
What happens when the ghost
is smart, and you know it?
So you use Minimax.
Well, you're not going to go for the
dot, because you know it's going to
get on top of you, and
you're going to die.
And so you kind of lead it on a chase,
and you do the safe thing.
And you are in a position in this
board that you can force a win.
Great.
You'll notice the score was
lower because I had to go
the long way around.
And that's just true.
The world is worse in a case where you
have an adversary then when you don't.
So it's not surprising that
the score is lower.
It doesn't mean you did
something wrong.
It just means the world was worse.
What happens when you get
your assumptions wrong?
Well, what happens when there's a smart
ghost who's going to come right
for you, but you don't know that?
Well, you're going to take a risk, and
the ghost is coming right at you, but
you just can't imagine it's true.
You keep taking these risks.
And maybe it works out,
or maybe it doesn't.
That time it worked out.
What happens when the ghost is random,
but you assume it's out to get you?
Right, this is vampire bunny.
Well, you're being pessimistic, so
it shouldn't be too dangerous.
It's actually not particularly
efficient.
So you run away, and what
does the ghost do?
It just kind of does its thing.
But you're scared, right?
Because at any point, you're like any
moment now, it's going to bust out its
master plan, right?
Oh, random number generator.
Until at some point--
no.
All right, so we could do
that a bunch of times.
I did it five times.
That's not really a statistically
adequate number, but you can look at
the outcomes here.
Basically, the only thing that's
actually dangerous, the only thing
that's going to get Pac-Man killed is
an adversarial ghost that you assume
is not out to get you, right?
If you're overly optimistic,
Pac-Man might actually die.
He gets mugged.
In the other cases, though,
take a look.
Expectimax Pac-Man with
a random ghost.
It's using the right model, and you get
503 because life's pretty good.
No one's out to get you.
Minimax and adversary, you still win.
You're still safe.
The score is lower, and the score is
lower because the world's just worse.
What about the last case, when there's
a random ghost and Minimax Pac-Man?
Well, you still win.
It just takes a while, and you
saw a case where it actually
took a very long time.